Trapped outside the boundaries of time and space... 102
aircraft... 6,000 men... all missing.
The Final Countdown is a war, action, science
fiction film directed by Don Taylor.
During routine manoeuvres near Hawaii in 1980, the aircraft-carrier USS Nimitz is caught in a strange vortex-like
storm, throwing the ship back in time to 1941—mere hours before the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor.
Capt. Matthew Yelland, played by Kirk Douglas.
Warren Lasky, played by Martin Sheen.
Laurel Scott, played by Katharine Ross.
Wing Commander Richard T. Owens, played by James Farentino.
Commander Dan Thurman, played by Ron O'Neal.
Senator Samuel Chapman, played by Charles Durning.
The Final Countdown is a 1980 American science fiction war film about a modern, nuclear-powered aircraft
carrier that travels through time to the day before the December 7, 1941, attack on Pearl Harbor.
It is directed by Don Taylor, his final theatrical film as director, and stars Kirk Douglas,
Martin Sheen, James Farentino, Katharine Ross, Ron O'Neal, and Charles Durning.
The film was produced with the cooperation of the United States Navy's naval
aviation branch and the United States Department of Defense.
It was set and filmed on board USS Nimitz (CVN-68), filming operations of the
modern, nuclear warship, which had been launched in the early 1970s.
Troma Entertainment founder Lloyd Kaufman was an associate
producer of the film, and also has a minor acting role.
The Final Countdown was released by United Artists on August 1, 1980.
It received mixed reviews from critics, but was a
moderate success at the box office.
It received Saturn Award nominations for Best Science
Fiction Film and Best Actor (for Kirk Douglas).
The film explores themes of airplane, world war ii,
time travel, pearl harbor, pacific war.
The tone is thought_provoking.